RUBIERE RAMIREZ

Geospatial Specialist | Spatial Data Engineer

rubiere.ramirez@gmail.com

(+501) 636-5355



Q 19 Barton Creek Street, Belmopan City, Belize

github.com/rubi3r3

SUMMARY

A geospatial specialist and a spatial data engineer with over six years of experience in proprietary geographic information systems (GIS), free and open-source GIS, spatial data programming, spatial database management, remote sensing, earth observation, and spatial data engineering.

EXPERIENCE

Geographic Information Systems Assistant, **Statistical Institute of Belize**

■ September 2022 – Present

Q Belmopan, Belize

Administer and maintain Enterprise GIS, spatial databases, services, Web GIS applications and perform earth observation on the built environment.

- Develop, administer and maintain spatial databases on PostgreSQL database with PostGIS extension.
- Develop, administer and maintain web applications on free and opensource software for geospatial (FOSS4G): GeoServer & Mapstore2; and on commercial off-the-self (COTS) software: Portal for ArcGIS & ArcGIS Server.
- Create Sentinel-2 Geomedian of Belize with Google Earth Engine and classify urban areas with machine learning in Python.
- Develop tools to automate tasks and to standardize the extraction, transformation and loading of non-spatial data and spatial data into SIB's spatial data repositories with SQL, R, and Python.

Geographic Information Systems Technician,

Statistical Institute of Belize

■ July 2018 – September 2022 **Q** Belmopan, Belize

Create spatial data using front-end geospatial software and produce maps.

- Heads-up digitized building footprints for the entire country of Belize.
- Perform remote sensing techniques to detect changes in urban areas in
- Process aerial photos from drone imagery in QGIS and ArcGIS Pro.

Geographic Information Systems Technician,

Coastal Zone Management Authority and Institute of Belize

♀ Belize City, Belize

Assist CZMAI with data creation and field data collection.

- Heads-up digitized and updated building footprints for Caye Caulker using Google Earth Pro and existing building footprints.
- Assisted with the collection of land use and building information in Caye Caulker using Open Data Kit for android devices.

EDUCATION

B.Sc. in Natural Resource Management

University of Belize

= 2012 – 2014

• Belmopan, Belize

SKILLS

R | R-Spatial | Python | GeoPython | SQL | Spatial SQL | QGIS | ArcGIS Pro | Geographic Data Science | Data Engineering | Remote Sensing | Earth Observation | PostgreSQL PostGIS | FOSS4G GeoServer | Geovisualization and Geocommunication | Web GIS

ACHIEVEMENTS

Enterprise GIS in FOSS4G

Developed and implemented an Enterprise GIS infrastructure with free open-source software geospatial: QGIS and PostgreSQL Database with PostGIS extension.

Web GIS in FOSS4G

Deployed and maintained Open-Source GeoServer and Mapstore2 with Apache Tomcat on Apache HTTP Server on SIB's GIS Servers.

Web GIS Development: Full-**Stack PERN Application**

Built and maintained PostgreSQL, Express, React, Node.is geoportal to geovisualize the Statistical Institute of Belize's spatial data.

GIS Web Application for Census Progress Tracking

Geovisualized census progress coverage by creating a web application using open standards: Mapstore2 web created using GeoServer. PostgreSQL database with PostGIS extension and ETL process automated with R programming.

Created {rvr2spatial}

A package in R programming designed to facilitate the ETL process from MariaDB to PostgreSQL PostGIS.